# Osty Leon (english version) Backend Developer | Data Engineer | System Engineer Senior

Whatsapp: (+55) 51 9 89266692
Email: leonscrumdev@gmail.com
Location: Curitiba, Paraná, Brazil.

Linkedin: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ooleondev/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/ooleondev/</a>

GitHub: https://github.com/ooleon/

Languages: Spanish (Native), English (Advanced),

and Portuguese.

Profile: Professional with over 15 years in IT as Data Engineer, Software Engineer, Backend Developer, Scrum Master, Agil Coach, and including Management in several kinds of companies like oil company, health, bank, financial, telecom, consulting, among others companies. I feel comfortable working remotely as a Software Engineer. I'm a team player, I really like learning and teaching. I recently used this technologies Java Spring Boot Hibernate Apache libraries, and common open-source frameworks Oracle PL/SQL Microservice hexagonal architecture, Rest, Testing tools AWS and others, in an international English project for archive the German government's requirements. I have continually practiced myself with new technologies.

#### **Skills & Qualifications:**

Java, Python, C#, CSharp, .Net, Spring, Django, Critical Thinking, Analytical Thinking, Training, Consultancy, System analysis, Requirements analysis, projects documentation, Clean Code, Domain Architectures, Hexagonal architecture, ports and adapters architecture, Clear Code, Solid principles, Integrations, Scrum Foundations Certification, Technical Presentations, Business Requirements, Agile Environment, Teamwork, Database normalization, Test-Driven Domain-Driven Behavioral-Driven Development, Backend Development, Flask, Microservices, Workflow, Testing, Loggs, Log4J, JUnit, Mockito, Unit Test, Automation Test, TestNG, RPA, BPA, BAW, Business Automation Workflow, Case Management, BPM, Oracle Workflow, UML, BPMN, Spring Boot, Spring MVC, Spring Data, Spring Cloud, Spring Bach, Spring WebFlux, Struts, JPA, Hibernate, OMR, MVVM (Model-view-viewmodel), Entity Framework, RDBMS, Oracle, PL/SQL, Postgresql, MySQL, SOL Server, IBM DB2, NoSQL, Elasticsearch, MongoDB, Redis, SSIS, Transact Sql, Message Broker, Message Queuing, JMS, MQ, RabbitMQ, Karaf, Camel, Kafka, Microservice, ServiceBus, J2SE, J2EE, Jaspert, Ireport, Crystal Report, WebService, RESTFul, API Rest, Soap, WebSocket, Kibana Grafana, GraphQL, WebSphere, WebLogic, WebMethod, Tomcat, Pivotal, Jboss, Jboss Fuse, Apache Tomcat, Jakarta, IIS (Internet Information Server), Macros Excel, Excel Advanced, Visual Basic for Applications VBA, Access, BI ETL, Power BI, MicroStrategy, Tableau, Pentaho, ERPNext, Open ERP, Odoo ERP, Open Bravo, SAP (basic), Prototype, Google Web Toolkit, GWT, SoapUi, CI/CD, Jenkins, SonarQube, Selenium Webdriver, Cypress, Appium, Swagger, Maven, Graddle, Enterprise Architect, Microsoft Project, Github, GIT, Docker, Kubernetes, Kotlin, Node.js, NPM, TypeScript, Trello, Miro, Kanban board, Cloud Computing, AWS, AWS RDS SNS SQS EC2 Lambda, GCP, Unix Linux, Debian, Ubuntu, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Theano, SciPy, Beautiful Soup, Requests, Pipenv.

## **Professional experience**

- 1. **Developer** (Meta Brazil / CLT) 03/2021- 04/2022
  - Contribute to the development of healthcare software in the midst of the global pandemic in international **English-speaking** teams. Complete German government requirements regarding healthcare software in record time. Documenting in English and German. Implement new functions for a healthcare software in **Java/Oracle, Spring, Node, TypeScript** attending Client's requirements in several countries (Brazil, Germany, Poland, Japan). Working in an English global development team for implementing healthcare software in several countries. Actively applying methodologies and patterns such as Scrum, Solid, Testing, Loggs, Microservice, ServiceBus, Domain and Hexagonal Architectures, and helping training others developers and users, and Backend Development of health software to attend in the midst of the global pandemic health centers with a global reach. Interaction with the metrics and requirements to increase characteristics over time. Observation, monitoring and analysis of BI's metrics in Power BI for performing development in Backend.

References: Check <u>recommendations</u>.

- Developer (DNANet Brazil / CLT) 03/2020- 06/2020
  - Development and Implementations Microservice, Java, Middleware Jboss Fuse, Postgresql, in Cloud AWS, GCP, Azure, applying Rest, SOAP.Java, Developer Backend, Oracle PL/SQL, microservice. Development Java SE, JPA, Spring, Spring Boot, Weblogic, Jboss AS, Cloud, Apache Camel, Kafka, AWS, JUnit, Node.js, React.js, etc; This job opportunity was canceled by the pandemic.
- 3. Senior Systems Analyst (Accenture Brazil / CLT) 10/2018- 07/2019

  Senior Systems Analyst (focus in Microservice, Java, Oracle, Developer Backend, QA Test, Automation and Backlog for TDD) Develop Unit and Automated testing in Java/Oracle.

  Generate Company Value by documenting automated test manuals for awarenessing of other professionals. Software Development. Manager of support cases. Analysis BI pipelines and BI service. Development of ETL pipelines, Kanban Backlogs Requirements implemented in Java MicroService with Cucumber through Testing. Facilitate consultations to Juniors Developers. Documentation tests. Apply Java development experience to troubleshoot source code problems.

References: Check recommendations.

**Analist Management Specialist** 

information systems at the same time.

7.

4. **Data Engineer / Software Engineer (**Banplus Banco Universal)

06/2016 - 03/2017

- Migrating and Developing more than 200 Financial microservice and Scripts around Python Java and C#.Net, Spring Data, to create BI ETL data sources for migrating as well as data testing scenarios, Rest and SOAP services for Power BI. Development and Implementations Microservice for Commercial Banking, using Java, Middleware Jboss Fuse, WebMethod, Workflow, .Net Framework, Windows Server, IIS, Postgresql, in Cloud AWS, GCP, Azure, applying Rest, SOAP. Developing Financial microservice and Scripts in Python, Django, Flask, .Net C# Microsoft SQL Server Oracle PostgreSQL to create BI ETL data sources for migrating data testing scenarios, Rest, SOAP. Collaborate with cross-functional teams. Support the Android development team in Kotlin. Develop micro-services aligned with the company's technical architecture and business objectives. Apply in development object-relational mapping (ORM) frameworks. Create data sources for Power BI, MicroStrategy. Develop backend services and APIs using Python, C# and Java, ensuring high performance, scalability and reliability. Use of containerization technologies like Docker and container orchestration tools like Kubernetes for test deployment in development. Collaborate with architecture team to solve problems and with financial and economics functional teams to test results.
- 5. **Scrum Master** Z-Zeus Consultores C.A. 10/2012 04/2014
  Functions: Implementing Scrum methodology. Coordination of development staff. Facilitate, lead, and communicate, to promote, support, and ensure the Scrum Process is understood and lived in the organization. Helping the team solve problems. Management and monitoring of projects, Training and coordination of programmers, Support to the management and monitoring of the project; Administration, Development and Maintenance of software. Scrum Master focused on implementing the architecture of an ERP Prototype.
- 6. **Product Owner PO** Z-Zeus Consultores C.A. 01/2010 10/2012
  Functions as Position: Product Owner PO (researching to provide design for architecture prototype of an ERP). Perform Survey of Business Requirements; Design thinking Document UML processes of ERP solution, as well as training of programmers; software development and maintenance remotely; **Java** tester, SQL Developer; Survey, analysis and documentation. Managing the product backlog. Product Backlog Refinement. Create user stories and Prioritize. Product vision. Communicating with other stakeholders. Development stages and Evaluating progress. •Taking requirements, validation and monitoring with the user. •Specification of functional use case designs and diagrams; Instruct and coordinate development staff on their roles facilitating the development process; PO and PMO Scrum. Investigate requirements for ERP by re-engineering other ERP programs such as DataPro, Open Bravo, Profit Plus, **Python**, Open ERP, ERPNext. Personnel in Charge: 5 developers.
- BI Analyst, Software supplier's Coordinator, Automation Testing, Software Development, •Survey of Business Requirements Project monitoring, Interaction with customers and suppliers, •Use of BI Pentaho, and Traditional ETL using **Python** and PL/SQL in SAP and Oracle Financials for support users of Financials Departments. Hexagonal Architecture. Feel proud as Developer BackEnd of a system from scratch that replaced another app called "Remedy" based saving \$ 40 thousand USD per year to the company just before the beginning inflation extreme of Venezuela. Training of users. Documentation of projects and systems in BPMN, User management, Requirements taking, validation and monitoring with the user. Maintenance and administration of Project Information System (SIP +) a WorkFlow SqlServer based / BPM integrated to the platform and Java Oracle Developer for two

(Telefónica Movistar) 06/2008 - 01/2010

**Software Engineer / Data Engineer** PDVSA – Venezuela's Oils Company 01/2005 - 06/2008 8. Development and recovery of information system Java, Struts, Oracle PLSQL, SQL Server, J2SE, Jaspert, Ireport, Cristal Reports, Jakarta Tomcat, Jboss, GlassFish, WebMethod, Workflow, Unix HPUX. .Net Framework, Windows Server, IIS, • Developed strategical BI a statistical script and Dashboard for Reporting to direction level of the organization. • Maintenance of stratification of oil projects in Python DJango, NumPy, Matplotlib, SciPy, Oracle PLSQL, Sql Server. • Development of information systems and management of social projects in .Net, C# Sql Server. • Development Microservice as data source in Java Python C# for generate BI Bussines Intelligence Dashboards and Reports for others apps and departments. • Generate BI Bussines Intelligence and Reports in hydrocarbon management. • Apply Functional and Unit Tests. • Document in UML. • JUnit Automated Testing. • Functional and automated testing. • User training facilitator. • Functional Requirements Analyst. • Recover systems due to sabotage. • After a while, I returned in 2016 to PDVSA as a Freelance, developing a Pentaho application for data integration, OLAP services, reports, information dashboards, data mining and extraction, transformation, loading (ETL) using Python scripts. Supported a petroleum management project application using Postgres **Python Django** and created data sources for **Power BI**, **MicroStrategy**.

9. **COCA COLA – FENSA. – Caracas, Venezuela** 05/2003 - 12/2003

System Developer. Tecnologies: .Net C#, SQL Server, Transact SQL.

10. Barsa Planeta de Venezuela - British Editorial 01/2003 – 05/2003.

System Developer. Tecnologies: Visual Basic, SQL Server, Transact SQL.

11. Bureau of Accountants, Oswaldo Sarmiento and Associates. O.A.S. 10/2000-01/2003

Technical Advisory and Systems Developer. Technologies: Visual Basic, SQL Server, Transact SQL.

12. Central Bank of Venezuela / BCV (Banco Central de Venezuela) – 01/1999-09/2000

Technical Advisory Systems Developer, Systems Analyst.

Y2K event Tester and Consultancy for users.

Tecnologies: Microsoft Access, VBA Visual Basic para aplicação, Macros de Excel, Oracle PL/Sql, Sql Server, SQL Server, Transact SQL.

#### **Education**

2007 - 2014 <u>U.N.E.F.A.</u> "Universidad Nacional Experimental Politécnica de las Fuerzas Armadas" Master in Management of Information and Communication Technologies.

• 2000 - 2005 <u>U.A.H.</u> "Universidad Alejandro de Humboldt" Informatic Engineer.

 1993 - 1997 <u>I.U.T.A.</u> "Instituto de Tecnologia de Gestão Industrial" Informatic Engineering Technician.

#### References

- Eng. Raphael dos Santos rvsantos97@gmail.com +5547984288886
- Eng. Vilson Tauchen vilson.tauchen@outlook.com +5551991330845
- Eng. Bladimir Rondón pigbar@gmail.com (+506) 8557 9549
- Eng. Samuel Vivas -(+58) 414-9232097

#### Courses

- 2009- SAP 01 Overview Course. Length: 3 Days. Institution: Latino SAP America Caribbean, Centro Letonia Building. Caracas Venezuela.
- 2007 "Installation and Administration Course Pentaho. Management Tools of Business Intelligence
  (BI). Duration: 2 Days. Place: Computer Management XXI / CPM Matrix Solution, Caracas
  Venezuela. 3. 2005 Specialization Application Development e-Business. Certification IBM
  Advanced Career Education (IBM ACE) Programing Object Oriented and Web Applications. (J2EE,
  EJB, Servlets, JMS, JDBC, Swing, UML, XML, MVC, SQL). Training Program for Web Business
  Technology.
- Institution: IBM of Venezuela, 1 year and 4 months.
- 2019 DevOps, Duration: 5 Day, Accenture Brazil.
- 2018 Metodología Agile Scrum. SFPC Scrum Foundation Professional Certificate Portuguese. Autoridad emisora CertiProf
- 2015 -Bonita BPM Camp for LATAM , Length 1 Day, BonitaSoft webinar online.
- 2015 Bonita BPM User Authentication through LDAP o SSO, Length 1 Day, BonitaSoft webinar online.
- 2012 -Webinars Online: Power BI, Documentum, Selenium IDE, Microstrategy.
- 2006-English Language Course (Intermediate Level B2) Institution: UCV Modern Language Duration: 1 year and a half.

### Certifications

- Certification Scrum Foundations Professional Certificate in Idiom Portuguese / CertiProf International
- Certification Professional Developer Java / IBM.
- Course SAP Overview / SAP Latam.
- Course Oracle PL/SQL / Udemy
- Course DevOps / Meta

(See the following pages for attachments.)



## SCRUM FOUNDATION PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE (SFPC)

# Osty Leon

Has completed the requirements to be recognized as SCRUM FOUNDATION PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATE (SFPC)

Date of Certification

Sat 12th Jan 2019

EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR

The global independent certification institute for Professionals

This certificate remains property of CertiProf LLC and shall be returned immediately upon request



CertiProf® is a registered trademark of CertiProf, LLC in the United States and/or other countries.



**IBM Training** 

## **IBM Advanced Career Education**

Professional certificate

This certifies that

## LEON OSTY

has successfully completed the

Mando Than

## IBM Advanced Career Education e-business Application Developer Program

and has passed the assessment test for the following modules:

Enterprise Application Development

Marcelo Roman

Director

IBM Global Leader for Learning Delivery

Dated: May 20, 2005

S/N: VEMCT000413





**IBM Training** 

## **IBM Advanced Career Education**

Associate certificate

This certifies that

## LEON OSTY

has successfully completed the

## IBM Advanced Career Education e-business Application Developer Program

and has passed the assessment test for the following modules:

IT Fundamentals
Programming Essentials
Object Oriented, Java and DB Programming

Marcelo Roman

Director

IBM Global Leader for Learning Delivery

Mando Ham

Dated: May 20, 2005

S/N: VEMCT000268

# **CERTIFICADO**



Osty León
Asistió al Curso SAP01
Overview

Del 30 de Marzo al 01 de Abril de 2009

Inés Eugenia Castro Gerente Regional de Operaciones Educación

**EN SAP ANDINA Y DEL CARIBE** 

SAP Education

THE BEST-RUN BUSINESSES RUN SAPT





#### Letter of Reference from the owner/CEO of Z-Zeus.

San José, Costa Rica, 12 de Setembro de 2018.

A quem possa interessar:

Informo que Osty Oscar Leon Fuentes trabalhou comigo na empresa Z-Zeus Consultores C.A. como Consultor, Analista de Requisitos e Arquitecto de Software. Trabalhamos juntos na área de Investigacion y Desarrollo de Software. Gostaria de recomendá-lo para uma posição em sua empresa.

Enquanto trabalhou na empresa citada acima, o desempenho e a conduta de **Osty Oscar Leon Fuentes** foram sempre exemplares. **Ele** sempre se mostrou apto a ajudar a equipe explicando com detalhes as atividades, tirando dúvidas e delegando responsabilidades. É detalhista e tem perfeito domínio do conhecimento técnico.

Ele sempre se distinguiu por consistentemente submeter trabalhos muito bem desenvolvidos nos prazos requeridos e de muita qualidade. Considero-o muito inteligente e tem excelentes habilidades analíticas e de comunicação.

Se eu puder acrescentar mais algum detalhe de seu trabalho, por favor queira contatar-me diretamente no telefone (+506) 8557 9549 ou e-mail pigbar@gmail.com

Atenciosamente,

Eng. Bladimir Rondón





#### CONSTANCIA

Se hace constar que el (la) Ciudadano (a) **LEON OSTY** portador (a) de la Cédula de Identidad Nº 12.400.035, presta sus servicios en esta empresa asignado a **TELCEL C.A.**, desde el Veintitrés (23) de Junio de 2008 hasta la actualidad, como **ESPECIALISTA DE GESTIÓN**, devengando un sueldo mensual de Cuatro mil doscientos dieciocho con 00/100 Bolívares Fuertes (Bs. F. 4.218, 00)

Constancia que se expide a petición de la parte interesada en Maracaibo el día Dieciocho (18) del mes de Agosto del año Dos Mil Nueve.

Por ITTACA CORP, C.A.

Ing. Eli R. Lobo Vice Presidente

